Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers, 1880, 1919-1998 and undated RL.10086
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Personal and Family Materials, 1919-1998 and undated; 3; 27 Boxes
  - Finkelstein, 1950-1970 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    Correspondence primarily from Louis Finkelstein to Heschel on a variety of administrative and personal topics including promotions, salary increases, thank yous, class schedules, and invitations to speak/attend events. Also includes a few draft letters from Heschel to Finkelstein.
  - Concert, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    Mix of materials related to Sylvia Heschel's piano recital at Town Hall in New York, including press release, program, seating plan of Town Hall and handwritten notes related to free tickets, entry tickets, Box Office statements and expenses related to the recital, and handwritten lists of invites, attendees, and those who didn't attend.
  - Town Hall Recital Reviews and Telegrams, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    Mix of materials related to Sylvia Heschel's piano recital at Town Hall in New York, including program, telegrams wishing her well, and coupons for entry into the recital.
  - Festival, 1951-1952 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    Administrative documents related to The Scholars Festival Foundation.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1951-1953 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Mix of materials including correspondence from various admirers and acquaintances, programs to conferences that Heschel spoke at, schedules of classes (including those taught by Heschel), and various clippings.
  - Jackson, 1951-1955 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    Primarily bulletins related to book reviews and conferences presumably attended by Heschel.
  - דת ה-ו, TI, 1952, 1955 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    Transliteration: Dat 5-6
    Translation: Religion 5-6
    A page of handwritten notes, an exam on religion from 1952 and a Progress Report form for a religion class from 1955, presumably all from the Teachers Institute (TI).
  - French, 1953, 1964, 1971-1972, 1997-1998 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    Primarily correspondence, including several letters from Idamarie Solltman, correspondence from Maurice Jacobs regarding the Diesendruck manuscript, letters from admirers of Heschel, and correspondence related to the 25th anniversary of Heschel's death. Also includes black and white photograph of unknown man and typed notes on a talk by Rabbi J.B. Soloveitchek.
  - Denver, 1953-1955 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Mix of correspondence, clippings, and program related to Heschel's appearance at the B'nai B'rith annual Mountain State Institute of Judaism in Denver, Colorado.
  - Guggenheim, 1953-1954 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    Mix of correspondence, typescript, and handwritten notes related to Heschel's application for and receipt of the Guggenheim Fellowship. Also includes all application materials and relevant documentation of award.
  - [Examination Books], 1954 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    Examination blue books from Heschel's students at the Jewish Theological Seminary.
  - Ab's Letters, 1955, 1972, 1981-1982 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    Primarily copies of legal materials including the Heschel's marriage certificate, Heschel's death certificate and social security.
  - Important, 1955-1963 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    Mix of administrative and personal correspondence related to a variety topics including publicity for Heschel's books, Vietnam, and reactions to some of Heschel's addresses. Personal correspondence is from former students and acquaintances, most notably Henry Allen Moe and Gerhard von Rad. Also includes Heschel's travel schedule for 61/62 and some handwritten notes.
  - Interior Decorating, 1955-1976 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Mix of invoices, correspondence, plans, and receipts related to decorating of the Heschel's apartment.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1956, 1964-1982; 1 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    Language(s): Some materials in Hebrew and Italian.
    Mix of materials including programs from events honoring Heschel after his death, clippings primarily about Martin Luther King's death, a telephone directory from Jewish Theological Society, and a few color slides of Sylvia and Susannah Heschel. Also contains a few articles written about Heschel after his death, including "Problemi di Filosophia di Teologia Christiana in Abraham Joshua Heschel" by Albino Babolin.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1956, 1964-1982; 2 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Medical, 1956-1957, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Miscellaneous prescriptions and EKG's.
  - Family: [Ideological Conference], 1957 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    Language(s): Most materials in Hebrew
    Clippings and a few miscellaneous documents related to a trip to Jerusalem for the "Ideological Conference" held August 8-16, 1957.
  - [Ideological Conference], 1957 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    A mix of transcripts and essays. Includes "The Shifting Meaning of Zionism" by Dr. Joseph B. Schechtman and transcripts from the Ideological Conference.
  - Letters, Programs, Cards, 1957, 1964-1968 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    Mix of personal correspondence (including letter from Lotte Jacobi), holiday and birthday cards, and various programs to events at the Dalton School and Sylvia Heschel's recital at the Manhattan School of Music.
  - [Certificate, Pan American-Grace Airways], 1958 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    Certificate presented to Heschel by Pan American-Grace Airways (Panagra) for crossing the Equator en route from Panama to La Paz.
  - South Am., 1958 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Language(s): Some materials in Yiddish and Spanish.
    Contains receipts, business cards, clippings, notes, and correspondence related to a trip to South America.
  - South America, 1958 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    Language(s): Most materials in Spanish, German, and Yiddish.
    Mix of materials including correspondence, bulletins, and announcements related to Heschel's trip to San Paolo, Rio de Janeiro, and St. Thomas.
  - [Conference notes], 1958, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Contains typed transcript from the Union of American Hebrew Congregation Committee on Worship Research Conference of Jewish Scholars, December 29-30, 1959 in which Heschel was in attendance. Also includes partially annotated handwritten and typed address possibly from same conference, and clippings on race relations.
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1961; 1 of 3 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    A mix of correspondence from admirers and colleagues, event programs, synagogue bulletins and clippings mainly related to speeches and publications of Heschel's. Includes a letter from Emil Fackenheim and a copy of a petition sent to the Claims Conference requesting $20,000 for work with Jewish children affected by the War in Europe in 1961, a letter from former students of Heschel's struggling with the lack of attention to Jewish practice they are finding in suburban Jewish communities, and one letter each from Sylvia and Susannah Heschel.
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1961; 2 of 3 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1961; 3 of 3 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    A mix of correspondence from admirers and colleagues, event programs, synagogue bulletins and clippings mainly related to speeches and publications of Heschel's. Includes a letter from Emil Fackenheim and a copy of a petition sent to the Claims Conference requesting $20,000 for work with Jewish children affected by the War in Europe in 1961, a letter from former students of Heschel's struggling with the lack of attention to Jewish practice they are finding in suburban Jewish communities.
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1964; 1 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    A mix of correspondence from colleagues and admirers, event programs and clippings. Contains programs for two different conferences on religion and race - one in Buffalo, New York and one in New York City. Also includes a number of letters from Sylvia and Susannah Heschel.
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1964; 2 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - [Photograph - Heschel by Jewish Theological Society], 1959 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    Black and white publicity photograph of Heschel by the Publicity Office of the Jewish Theological Society.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1959, 1967-1969 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    Primarily postcards and greeting cards, but also contains a small amount of correspondence to both Heschels.
  - Minnesota, 1959-1960 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Mix of correspondence, clippings, printed leaflets, posters, and receipts all related to Heschel's visiting professorship at the University of Minnesota in the spring of 1960.
  - [Miscellaneous], circa 1950s (Box 31, Folder 2)
    Language(s): Most materials in French.
    Primarily contains French exercises by Sylvia Heschel, but also includes a small amount of correspondence, handwritten notes (related to music), and newsletters.
  - [Miscellaneous], circa 1950s-1970s; 1 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Primarily notebooks containing lessons for practicing Hebrew and French which appear to have belonged to Sylvia. Also contains an Alumni Directory for the Manhattan School of Music and Sylvia's business card advertising private piano lessons.
  - [Miscellaneous], circa 1950s-1970s; 2 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - [Correspondence], 1960, 1963 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Mix of personal letters and notes to Sylvia Heschel primarily from family members.
  - Iowa, 1960-1961 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    Mix of correspondence, pamphlets, bulletins, and course syllabi all related to Heschel's visiting professorship at the State University of Iowa in the spring of 1961.
  - [Roll Book], 1960-1961 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    A roll book for Heschel's classes at the Teachers Institute and at the Jewish Theological Seminary.
  - Abbell, 1960-1961, 1965 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    Correspondence and legal documents related to a partnership in a shopping center in Illinois.
  - [Miscellaneous Documents], 1960-1961, 1972 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    Includes handwritten notes, a gradebook for Heschel's Jewish Philosophy in the Middle Ages class from 1960-1961 and photocopies. Also includes a typed document of the Rabbinical Assembly titled, "Model Agreement with Congregation."
  - Policy Statements and Recommendations from the White House Conference on Aging, 1961 Feb (Box 32, Folder 3)
    Bound report from the White House Conference on Aging, in which Heschel participated.
  - [Press Clippings], 1961 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    A few clippings that mention Heschel and his work.
  - Mr. Weinberg, 1961-1965; 1 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    Contains annotated appointment calendars from 1961-1965. Also includes a newspaper clipping about Dr. Edward Teller.
  - Mr. Weinberg, 1961-1965; 2 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Mr. Weinberg, 1961-1965; 3 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - [Souvenir], 1962 (Box 45)
    Stone, wrapped in a Arabic newspaper, apparently a souvenir from a trip to Israel.
  - Fall Out, 1962-1963 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    Correspondence, program, agenda, and some handwritten notes primarily related to the Conference on Radiation and Social Ethics at which Heschel presented. Also includes correspondence related to article in Time Magazine and the Conference on Race and Religion.
  - Washington, 1963, 1965, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    A mix of publications, typescripts and handwritten notes related to a White House Conference on education that Heschel participated in. Includes the January 25, 1967, September 13, 1967 and December 6, 1967 issues of The Christian Century.
  - UTS: UTS, circa 1963-1966 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    Mix of annotated typescripts, correspondence, clippings, and handwritten notes related to Heschel's position at Union Theological Seminary and Christian-Jewish relations.
  - 1964 - Race, Age, 1964 February (Box 33, Folder 2)
    A copy of the "Retirement Planning News." Includes an article, "Some Sage Advice From Ethics Expert," about a paper Heschel presented at a conference on aging.
  - Suzy, 1964, 1970-1971 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    A mix of handwritten notes and correspondence. Also includes notes for a lecture at the Jewish Museum and handwritten notes to Heschel from Sylvia and Susannah.
  - [Miscellaneous newsclippings], 1964-1965; 1 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    Variety of clippings related to Heschel (from a clipping service).
  - [Miscellaneous newsclippings], 1964-1965; 2 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - [Miscellaneous Notes], circa 1965 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    A few pages of notes - mostly contact information and what appears to be flight information and prices.
  - Seminar, 1965 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    Handwritten notes and typescripts related to a seminar Heschel taught. Includes some correspondence.
  - [Calendars] (1 of 3), 1965, 1967, 1970-1972; 1 of 3 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    Five annotated appointment calendars.
  - [Calendars] (2 of 3), 1965, 1967, 1970-1972; 2 of 3 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - [Calendars] (3 of 3), 1965, 1967, 1970-1972; 3 of 3 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - All about Ab, 1965, 1974-1994 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    Contains a variety of materials primarily about Heschel after his death. Includes correspondence to Sylvia Heschel, clippings, bulletins, tributes and articles related to Heschel. Also includes a 1965 letter to Heschel from Yehuda Eidelstein.
  - [Correspondence], 1965-1966; 1 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    Primarily personal correspondence related to a variety of topics including letters from admirers of Heschel's books, invitations to lecture, thank yous for visits, and social justice topics such as Soviet Jewry and Vietnam. Most notable letters are from Emil Fackenheim and Maurice Friedman. Also includes invitations, clippings, programs where Heschel lectured, press releases, and reviews for books.
  - [Correspondence], 1965-1966; 2 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Dialogue, circa 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    A combination of materials sent to Heschel by P'eylei Israel regarding Christian Missionaries in Israel and correspondence to Heschel from various administrators and professors from Union Theological Seminary regarding lectures and meetings.
  - [Herzl Institute Bulletin], 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    Bulletins (primarily Volume 2) from the Herzl Institute.
  - UTS: Dr. Kennedy, circa 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    Administrative materials related to Heschel's position at Union Theological Seminary.
  - [Newspaper Clippings], 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    Newspaper clippings on a variety of topics including Martin Luther King's receipt of the Judaism and World Peace Award, Vietnam, Soviet Jewry, Jewish education, and Heschel's speaking engagements.
  - [Newspaper Clippings], 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    Newspaper clippings on a variety of topics including Vietnam, Vatican II, and Heschel's speaking engagements.
  - Schedule, 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    Primarily correspondence related to Heschel's various visits to West Coast institutions including Graduate Theological Seminary, San Francisco Theological Seminary and Stanford. Also contains some correspondence related to Heschel's honorary degree from Notre Dame.
  - UTS: UTS Archives, circa 1965-1966 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    Correspondence during Heschel's time at Union Theological Seminary, handwritten notes, and a newspaper clipping.
  - [Correspondence], 1965-1970 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    Mostly correspondence from colleagues and admirers and some clippings. Includes a letter from Jacob Heschel.
  - [Photograph - Heschel Berkeley], 1966 Feb (Box 35, Folder 1)
    Color photograph of Heschel in suit and bow-tie.
  - [Notre Dame Honorary Degree], March 1966 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    Heschel's Honorary Doctorate from the University of Notre Dame.
  - [Photograph - Heschel convocation], 1966 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    Three black and white photographs of Heschel receiving an honorary degree at St. Michael's College.
  - [Request], 1966 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    Contains a letter from the Academy of the Sacred Heart of Mary asking Heschel if he would speak on the topic of silence. Includes the publication Renewal, illustrated with color graphics by Sister Corita using texts by Heschel and others.
  - [Miscellaneous documents], 1966-1968 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    A mix of personal receipts, coupons, financial information, lists of people and handwritten notes.
  - Sylvia, 1967 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    Heschel family photos.
  - [Correspondence], 1967-1971 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    Correspondence from colleagues and admirers including many letters wishing Heschel well after an illness and condolences after Jacob Heschel passed away.
  - Seminaries, 1968 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    Contains sheets torn out of the annual catalogue for Bangor Theological Seminary.
  - St. Louis, 1968 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    Contains correspondence and programs related to conferences in St. Louis in which Heschel was a visiting participant. The programs were for a series at Washington University called "The Mystery of Man" and the First Sesquicentennial Conference at Saint Louis University entitled "Theology in the City of Man."
  - [Correspondence], 1968-1969 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    A mix of correspondence and clippings. Includes a pamphlet titled "Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam," and a pamphlet entitled "Vietnam and the Future of the American Empire which includes a meditation written by Heschel. Also includes correspondence related to Heschel's honorary doctorate from Saint Mary's College, and a letter from Elemire Zolla.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1968-1971 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    Mix of materials including handwritten notes, handwritten lists of individuals, several typed term papers from Heschel's students and a typed and annotated lecture about Yiddishkeit.
  - [Miscellaneous Documents], 1969, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of Talmud pages (tractate Yoma), excerpts from Pirkei Avot, a publication of The Student Organizations of JTS that includes an "In Memorium" section on Heschel and programs for the Honors Day Convocation at Park College.
  - [Correspondence], 1969-1970 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew and French.
    A mix of correspondence, handwritten notes and clippings. A fair amount of the correspondence is in reference to Heschel's health after he suffered a heart attack. Includes a letter from Congressman William F. Ryan.
  - Who's Who, 1969-1971 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    Correspondence related to Heschel's biography in "Who's Who in the East." Also includes a few programs and correspondence related to Heschel's position as the William James Lecturer on Religious Experience at Harvard for the Spring Term of 1970-1971.
  - Italy, 1969-1972 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    Contains a mix of handwritten notes, correspondence, bills and itineraries related to Heschel's visit to Italy.
  - [Address cards], circa 1960s; 1 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    Mix of business cards, envelopes, and scraps of paper, organized alphabetically with names and address of individuals Heschel knew.
  - [Address cards], circa 1960s; 2 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - [Photograph - Heschel by Friedman-Abeles], circa 1960s (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Black and white photograph of Heschel.
  - [Photographs - Heschel by John Popper], circa 1960s (Box 36, Folder 8)
    Two original black and white photographs and one copy of Heschel by John Popper.
  - [Photographs - Heschel by Lotte Jacobi), circa 1960s (Box 36, Folder 9)
    Three original black and white photographs of Heschel by Lotte Jacobi.
  - [Miscellaneous], circa 1960s-1970s (Box 36, Folder 10)
    Contains black and white photograph of Heschel with cigar by Herb Weitman, a proof of dust jacket for A Passion for Truth, a newspaper clipping about Chaim Grade, and two copies of a postcard reproduction of a portrait painting of Heschel by Henry Koerner.
  - [Heschel contribution], 1970 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    Receipt for financial contribution that Heschel made to Mesivta Tifereth Israel.
  - Honors & Prizes, 1970-1971 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    Invitations, correspondence, telegrams, and clippings primarily related to two awards received by Heschel: the Jewish Heritage Award from B'nai B'rith and the Israel Bond Testimonial Dinner.
  - USA, 1970-1971 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    Mix of materials including business cards, a photocopy of a letter from Dr. Pinchas Peli to Rabbi Wolfe Kelman regarding translation of some of Heschel's books, a note from Prof. Gedaliah Nigal, and handwritten biographical notes about Rabbis, public behavior, and faith.
  - Heritage, 1970-1971 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    Mix of congratulatory telegrams and correspondence, programs, press releases, and clippings related to Heschel's receipt of the Jewish Heritage Award from B'nai B'rith. Also includes a poster "An Appeal By Civil Rights Leaders For Soviet Jewry."
  - Memorabilia Ab, 1970-1973 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    Mix of correspondence, cards, and notes on a variety of topics. Also includes programs from events and memorials either attended by or honoring Heschel including a memorial for the students killed at Kent State University and the Ordination and Investiture Ceremonies of Hebrew Union College where Heschel received an honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters.
  - AJH, 1971; 1 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Mix of handwritten notes and typescripts which appear to be outlines for courses taught by Heschel including "Kiddush Ha-Shem, Sacrifice and Imitatio Dei" and "Basic Ideas of Judaism." Also includes clippings on Heschel receiving the Jewish Heritage Award.
  - AJH, 1971; 2 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - [Passport], 1971 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    Sylvia Heschel's passport.
  - [Telephone Directory], 1971 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    Telephone directory for the Jewish Theological Seminary.
  - Awards, 1971 and undated (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Programs for various awards honoring Heschel. Also includes invitation to surprise 25th anniversary party for Heschel and Sylvia.
  - [Letters from Susannah], 1971 and undated (Box 37, Folder 9)
    Letters from Susannah Heschel to her parents.
  - Menorah, 1971-1972 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Mostly correspondence and related materials regarding speaking engagements, including a handwritten itinerary. Also includes correspondence regarding support for Senator George McGovern's candidacy for the presidential nomination.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1971-1972 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    Includes a letter from Soma Morgenstern to the Heschels and a notebook with practice Hebrew letters.
  - [Minutes], 1972 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    Typed minutes of the Executive Board Meeting of the Central Conference of American Rabbis.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1972 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    Mix of materials including correspondence, minutes of Seminar Faculty meeting, dissertation topic proposals, and a letter of recommendation from Heschel.
  - Press, 1972 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Clippings about Heschel.
  - Israel, 1972 and undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
    Primarily notes and fragments that are addresses and telephone numbers of contacts. Also includes some telephone messages, a personal letter, and a black and white postcard of David Koigen.
  - Articles about Ab, 1972-1973 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    Mix of typescripts, correspondence, and clippings written in memory of Heschel. Authors include Prof. A. Ikuro Teshima and Bishop Melvin Wheatley. Also includes galley proof of Heschel's article "Reflections on Death" in Conservative Judaism.
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 1 of 7 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    Mix of cards and letters sent to Sylvia and Susannah Heschel after Heschel's death. Also includes some memorial cards and gifts made in honor of Heschel.
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 2 of 7 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 3 of 7 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 4 of 7 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 5 of 7 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 6 of 7 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - [Condolences], 1972-1973; 7 of 7 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Eternal Light, 1972-1973 (Box 39, Folder 5)